Are you a good driver and you always follow
safe driving habits? Do you maintain your
car's health like brakes and engine oil very
well? You can now get rewarded for that and
pay less premium on your car insurance. You
can do this with 'Pay As You Drive' or 'Pay
How You Use' policy which is introduced now
in India. In this video, I will explain how
to reduce your car insurance costs every year
using this new type of car insurance called
'Pay As You Drive' or 'Pay How You Use' insurance
policy.
Welcome to Save
and Invest Smartly!
The 'Pay As You Drive' policy is a part of
the sandbox initiative, where insurers can
experiment and test innovative financial products.
The sandbox approach gives an opportunity
to experiment and learn about new technology
and product, before it’s finally adopted
and offered to larger set of people. The insurance
company that has rolled out 'Pay As You Drive'
insurance policy is ICICI Lombard General
Insurance.
What is Pay As You Drive Insurance?
This is a telematics based car insurance for
which the premium is calculated based on how
you drive. That is, the premium for this insurance
policy is calculated based your driving behavior.
The insurance companies understand that there
is less risk when good driving behavior is
adopted and are ready to reward them by giving
discounts on the premium. So if you drive
better and safer, then your premium will be
far lesser than that of traditional insurance
policies.
What is telematics?
Telematics is a device that will be installed
in your car to track how you drive and analyze
if you have maintained safe speed, efficient
mileage and smooth driving.
How is the Sum Insured calculated?
Every vehicle has an IDV - Insured Declared
Value, fixed by the insurer based on the brand,
model and age of the vehicle. It may be approximately
equivalent to the market value of the vehicle.
For example, let us consider you own a
car. There will be a market value for your
car as per the model, age of the car, etc.
IDV is approximately equivalent to the market
value.
Hence if the market value of your car
is 500000, then the sum insured that you will
get on the insurance is Rs. 500000.
How is the insurance premium calculated?
Initial premium is arrived at based on
your age, driving experience and the safety
features in the car.
You may pay the premium only for the first
quarter to start with. Your driving score
will be calculated every quarter and premium
will be revised accordingly.
If you maintain good and safe driving
habits, your driving score will increase and
hence the quarterly premium will become lesser.
What are the Coverage Options available?
You may choose any of the 2 coverage options
available.
Option 1: Stand Alone Own Damage Cover
Own Damage Insuranceis a customized motorinsurancepolicy
designed to protect you and your insured vehicle
from yourown damages. That is, this policy
covers against any loss or damage to your
vehicle or its accessories due to:
1. Fire, explosion, self-ignition, accidental
damage
2. Transit, that is when the vehicle is shifted
from one place to another
3. Natural disasters like earthquake, flood,
cyclone, etc.
4. Burglary, theft, riot, etc.,
Option 2: Own Damage with Third Party
This option covers everything in Option 1
plus the third party coverage.
Third party policycovers theinsuredagainst
any legal liability arising out towards third
parties due to accidental injury or death
of a person and any damage caused to third
party property.
Lets see the Advantages of 'Pay As You Drive'
Insurance policy
You will pay low premiums if your driving
is good. That is if you drive safely, then
your driving score improves and premium decreases.
A Free telematics device is provided to
you to track your car's health and your driving
patterns. The insurance company will help
in installing this telematics device to your
car.
A telematics mobile app can be installed
in your mobile, so that you can track your
car's health, your driving score, weekly summary
of driving behavior, etc.
You will also get periodic tips to improve
your driving based on your driving score.
In future, this type of insurance can revolutionize
the vehicle insurance world.
If lets say, you are meeting with an accident,
then the telematics device can automatically
detect the accident and trigger alerts to
police and ambulance attaching your GPS location
details. This can make the rescue operation
faster.
The telematics can also send alert to
the insurer for road-side assistance and claim
processing.
By giving continuous feedback to drivers
about their driving habits, it will create
good and responsible drivers thereby reducing
the accidents.
How to apply for 'Pay As You Drive' policy?
If you want to get the insurance from ICICI
Lombard General Insurance,
visit www.icicilombard.com. You will see
various menu options.
Click on Products and then select the
option "Pay As You Drive".
You may scroll through the page and understand
the features of this new policy.
Currently ICICI Lombard has made this
policy available to only those who are already
on a telematics based policy like 'Pay As
You Use'. Hence if you already have 'Pay As
You Use' you may contact the insurer and add
this option.
In future I hope, this type will be extended
to new applicants as well.
The 'Pay As You Drive' policy will definitely
save you money on your car insurance if your
maintain good and safe driving habits. Give
it a try when you apply or renew your car
insurance next time. Let me know your thoughts
on this new policy type in the comments section.
Also, write down if you have more queries
on this.
Hope this video was helpful to you! Subscribe
and hit the bell icon to watch more such videos.
Give a thumbs up if you like the video. Thank
you!